Now the moment we've all been waiting for.
现在 我们已经等了很久
It's time to talk about lists in HTML.
是时候聊一下 HTML 中的列表了
Lists are amazing in real life and in web development.
不管是在现实生活还是 Web 开发中 列表都很重要
Let's say, one of the most useful structures that we have as humans.
可以说是最有用的结构之一
Think about how much of your life revolves around lists.
想一下你生活中会遇见多少列表
Lists for groceries, and lists for to do's,
杂货列表 待办事项清单
and lists for who to invite to your birthday party, top 10 songs.
你生日派对想要邀请的人的列表 或者你最喜欢的十首歌曲
Lists are everywhere in our world,
列表在生活中无处不见
and it's important that we be able to harness and reproduce that usefulness in code.
而且 能够复用代码中有用的部分 对我们来说也是非常重要的
So HTML offers two types of built-in list structures.
所以 HTML 提供了 2 种内置的列表结构
The first is an ordered list and the second is an unordered list.
第一种是有序列表 第二种是无序列表
It's a little self intuitive what these might mean.
你应该可以通过字面意思理解它们
But we're going to take a look at them in action so you can get a full understanding.
但是我们也会看看它们在实际中的表现 这样你就可以有一个全面的认识
Generally, an ordered list has a ranking to them.
一般来说 有序列表会有一个排名
They're numbered 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
编号为 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 等等
whereas an unordered list is just a list of things without a necessary hierarchy.
而无序列表就只是一堆列表 没有必要的顺序关系
This will make more sense in practice.
在实践中也是这样
So here we are back in VS Code,
我们回到 VS Code 中
and I now have a file called lists.html.
这里有一个叫做 lists.html 的文件
Here in the body again,
在 body 内部
let's start with unordered lists.
我们从无序列表开始
Lists are interesting because they actually require a couple sets of tags.
列表比较有趣 因为它实际上由几组标签组成
The first is ul,
首先是 ul 标签
ul stands for unordered list.
ul 代表着无序列表
Then inside the ul,
然后在 ul 内部
for each element that you want to make an item in your list,
对于你想放置的每一个列表项
you use an li tag,
你需要使用 li 标签
li like line item maybe.
li 意味着列表项
So here, I'll say,
在这里写上
Item 1, and then notice I'm still in between the opening and closing ul tags.
Item one 然后注意了 还是在 ul 标签内部
I'm going to add a second item to my list.
我会添加第二个列表项
This one is going to be a Unicorn Horn Balm,
这一项我们写上 Unicorn Horn Balm
in case our unicorn's,
以免我们的独角兽 ( unicorn )
horn is hurting or whatever.
受伤或者其他什么情况
Then let's add a third thing to our list.
我们再添加第三列表项
I'll make another li, Item 1 Unicorn Horn Balm,
我们添加一个新的 li 标签
and let's say garlic onion powder.
然后写上 garlic onion powder
It's going to be quite the party.
看起来好像会是一场派对
So now if I save this and come over to the browser,
现在如果我们保存一下并在浏览器里看看
voila, we see here a beautiful list.
好了 我们看见了一个不错的列表
What I could do is I could combine what we've learned, say,
我们也可以结合之前学习到的知识
and use an h1 tag to make a header on my list and I'll say,
在列表上方用 h1 标签添加一个标题
this is the grocery shopping list for Frank.
写上 grocery shopping list for Frank
Here, we have a title and our grocery shopping list.
这里我们有了一个标题和杂货店购物列表
But what if we wanted these things to actually be ordered?
但是我们如何让他们变成有序的列表呢？
It's a very, very similar process.
步骤几乎是相同的
Instead of ul, unordered list,
比起使用 ul 无序列表
the tag for an ordered list is ol, ordered list.
我们可以使用 ol 标签 也就是有序列表
So just for fun,
所以为了更有趣一点
let's actually see what happens if I copy these from here and put them right here.
让我们复制一份之前的内容看看会发生什么
So it's the same thing except I now have them in an ordered list,
看起来是一样的 除非我们把它改成有序列表
and here they are.
好了 出现了
You can see now instead of bullet points,
你可以看见之前的小黑点
they use the numbers 1, 2,
变成了数字 1, 2,
3, and that's all done automatically because they're inside the ol tags.
3, 这些都是自动完成的 因为它们被包裹在 ol 标签中
So again, HTML has two ways for us to do lists built-in;
再重复一次 HTML 提供了两种内置的列表
ordered lists and unordered lists.
有序列表和无序列表
Ordered lists use the tags ol and then li tag in between them,
有序列表使用 ol 标签 和 li 标签
while unordered lists use the tag ul with the same li tags in between them.
而无序列表使用 ul 标签 在内部同样使用 li 标签
This is just the beginning of what can be done with lists.
这只是关于列表的第一步
But why don't you go ahead and give it a shot yourself?
你可以自己动手先试一试
Get your skills building for the next set of advanced lists we might make.
为我们下一个阶段更高级的列表做好准备